<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the Eton-scholars at St. Mary le Bow on November 18, 1679 by Thomas Horn.</title>
            <author>Horne, Thomas, 1627?-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44507</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30339</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11296084</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11296084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44507)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1464:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the anniversary meeting of the Eton-scholars at St. Mary le Bow on November 18, 1679 by Thomas Horn.</title>
                  <author>Horne, Thomas, 1627?-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Samuel Carr ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published at the request of the stewards."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Education --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47338:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the ANNIVERSARY MEETING OF THE ETON-SCHOLARS, At St. <hi>Mary le Bow,</hi> on <hi>November</hi> 18. 1679.</p>
            <p>By <hi>THOMAS HORN,</hi> Fellow of <hi>King's-College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Chaplain to the Right Honourable <hi>HENRY,</hi> Earl of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Albans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the requeſt of the Stewards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Carr,</hi> at the <hi>King's-Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:47338:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47338:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PROV. 22.6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Train up a Child in the way that he ſhould go, and when he is old, he will not depart from it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT is delightful not only to me, but, I believe alſo, to every one of you (worthy fellow Scholars, as you have lately given me leave to call you) to behold the luſter of this ſolemn day: The intent of it is ſo commendable, the circumſtances ſo harmonious and beautiful. <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is to ſee Brethren to dwell together in Unity!</hi> So many Brethren of one fruitful Mother, the Daughter of a King! to ſee them ſo well united to pay their Gratitude and Honour to that <hi>Pareut</hi> in the face of the World! (a work ſo becoming her <hi>Children</hi>) eſpecially to ſee them begin with a dutiful acknowledgment to the great God, in whom all gratitude ſhould terminate! a deſign ſo worthy the nurture of our pious Mother. <hi>I was glad</hi> (as the Royal Prophet ſpeaks) <hi>when they ſaid unto me, Let us go into the houſe of the Lord:</hi> glad to ſee that <hi>thither the Tribes
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47338:3"/>go up to give thanks to the Name of the Lord.</hi> And now ſince you have aſſembled and met together to render God thanks for that bleſſing of Education, and all other benefits that we have received at his hands, and to beg his bleſſing upon us; I hope this pious Beginning will give an auſpicious influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the following part of your Solemnity. Eſpecially ſeeing that you ſeem to revive in ſome meaſure the Primitive Feaſts of Charity. I intend therefore to improve, as much as I can, theſe your Religious and grateful purpoſes, by offering to your conſideration ſome of thoſe bleſſed advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which a careful Education affords, according to the intent of the Text; that you may more effectually purſue your deſign of being in this Houſe of God, rendring to him all the Glory of all the gains you have made in that <hi>Royal Seat</hi> of Literature.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Train up a Child in the way that he ſhould go,</hi> we may underſtand the catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and informing him in the way of Religion, in which every one ſhould go: And alſo the training him up in other profitable Learning and Skill ſuitable to his ſtate, his capacity, his way of life that he is to follow, as the Margin ſays, <hi>in his way.</hi> By training him up when a <hi>Child,</hi> he ſeems to mean the taking the firſt opportunities of infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing into him each part of Wiſdom, as ſoon as he appears capable of receiving it. And to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47338:3"/>the Parent in this care of his Child, he adds, <hi>and when he is old he will not depart from it.</hi> The weight of which ſeems to conſiſt in this, That the advantages of Education are unqueſtionably great, ſo great, that the duration of them is as much as need be added for encouragement; for who is ſo ſolicitous about the continuance of a trifle? But as any thing appears valuable, our fears of the loſing it are anxious, and our thoughts are buſie about the preſervation of it, ſo that the greater the benefits of Education appear, there is the more force in that conſideration, that they will laſt 'till old Age. Wherefore the more fully I can repreſent the advantages of Education, firſt in <hi>Religion,</hi> and then alſo in <hi>other commendable know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> eſpecially when it is <hi>early;</hi> the more fully will both the Exhortation of the Text, and the Argument of it be anſwered, and the deſign of our being here ſatisfied.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Firſt Part</head>
               <p>And as we have begun our Solemnity with God, ſo let us take our firſt conſiderations from him, who is the Fountain of all Wiſdom, and whoſe Fear is the beginning of it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, The teaching us to remember our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor in the days of our Youth, lays that great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Wiſdom, The deſigning a good end of all our life, the preferring the beſt End, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to chooſe and perſue the directeſt means to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47338:4"/>that End; leſt we ſhould ſnatch up vile deſigns, or live we know not why, or ramble in our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of that which is good. This makes all our Actions regular and uniform, tending all to the glory of the Creator, as the circumference of an Arch to the Center, which is both the beauty and ſtrength of it, under all preſſures. This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuades us to value our time, and improve all our Powers with oare, as Talents once to be accounted for. It teaches us to requeſt comfortably the bleſſing of God upon all our endeavours, that Dew of Heaven that enriches all. And when we ſucceed, it invites us to return all to his honour; which makes the knowledge of nature, and all other skill, truly uſeful, ſubſervient to a great purpoſe, and ſanctifies all our temporal Affairs.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Secondly, 'Tis of great uſe through all our life to have the Foundation of Religion (the Chriſtian eſpecially) laid even; becauſe the more lofty and magnificent the Building is, the more remarkable a flaw in the top, does a little error in the Foundation make. They that have been taught the great ends of Religion, who know which are the weightier matters of the Law of God, and which are the leſs weighty, which are to be preferred, which are to be ſubſervient to a farther end; will not be ſcrupulous, or troubleſom to themſelves, and the World about <hi>Mint, and Cumin, and neglect Judgment, Mercy, and Faith.</hi> They
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47338:4"/>will not be led away with any Religious pretence that overthrows the grand Ends of true Religion, and his full wicked and ſecular Deſign: They will be apt to ſearch the Scriptures for that End for which they were written, which brings them to the Native ſenſe, and pious uſe of them in their life and converſation. This will not let them dare to vex any portion of Sacred Writing, wreſting it to ſerve a turn, and keep up the oppoſition of Doctrine, falſly ſo called. Finally, this prevents diſhonourable thoughts of God, and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions, or preſumptions, conſequent thereto.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, The initiating Youth in the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and uſing them to the practice of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, is the moſt approved Antidote againſt the infections of bad converſation, and other mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Temptations, which a young Man meets with when he firſt enters into the World. And he had need <hi>put on the whole Armour of God</hi> to ſtand againſt ſo many importunate perſuaſions, ſo many bad Examples, ſuch ſecret allurements to wickedneſs: He had need be well perſuaded of the value of Innocence and excellence of Piety: He had need be fully reſolved in his Heart not to depart from the fear of his God, leſt the rampant importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of profane wretches in their full cry, ſilence the ſofter whiſpers of his Conſcience. For how cheap a prey is a young unſetled Man! How ſoon is he run down by an unruly ſort of talk; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47338:5"/>forced to ſhelter his Modeſty from the imperious rebukes of a frolick Humour, by entring in, and being one of the Herd! But he only is armed againſt theſe aſſaults, whoſe mind is filled before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with the bright <hi>Idea's</hi> of God and Goodneſs, and whoſe Heart is engaged with the love of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The laying a good Foundation of Religion at firſt, renders the Man uſeful to others, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to Superiours, profitable to Church and State, peaceable, juſt in his Dealings, meek and cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in his Converſe, charitable in his Thoughts and Words, of Things and Perſons, ſteady in that Station in which God has placed him, without breaking the Harmony of the World, conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and induſtrious in his proper Calling. It fills the Mind with large benevolous Thoughts, good Deſires towards all, and an aim at public Good in all he does. You your ſelves are a great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation to Education in the work of this day. 'Tis a credit to our School, the very Deſign upon which you meet, ſuch benign public thoughts are a ſweet Fruit of good nurture, and I hope there will more of it ripen every day; that we may once be full of Goodneſs and Charity, as now of ſower humour and Religious ſpight. Would to God that happy day would once ariſe, when Men would uſe ſo much Charity, as to permit the old wounds in the Body of Chriſt to heal, and not induſtriouſly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47338:5"/>pierce his Hands and Feet, and Side afreſh! That the ſolid Duties of Humility and Chriſtian love would riſe, while pride and variance were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured down into the darkneſs from whence they came; that we might learn <hi>with one mind, and one mouth to glorifie God!</hi> If ever God will be pleaſed to grant that deſireable Bleſſing; the Seeds of it ſeem to be lodged in places of good Education. And ſuch deſigns as theſe are the promiſing Bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings forth of Peace. However, let us do our utmoſt, and fear we not, but that God will bleſs us in it. For 'tis ſaid of the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, They ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 123.6.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. That which enlivens all human endeavours, and is the greateſt encouragement to Parents, to take care of the pious Inſtitution of their Children in the fear of the Lord, is this, That the Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their firſt years to the honour of God, ſhrouds them under the ſhadow of his Wings; 'tis a waving their firſt Fruits of their days before the Lord, which bleſſes all the reſt; for he has given us illuſtrious Teſtimonies of his kind acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptance of ſuch Oblations, and of his Bleſſing upon them. When <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Mother had by Prayer obtained him of the Lord, ſhe devoted the Child gratefully to him. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.27, 28.</note> 
                  <hi>For this Child,</hi> ſaid ſhe, <hi>I prayed, and the Lord hath given me my Petition, which I asked of him; therefore alſo have I lent him unto the Lord as long as he liveth: He ſhall be lent unto the Lord.</hi> And this
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47338:6"/>was as kindly received. For though <hi>Samuel</hi> were not of that Sacred Tribe, which God had choſen to miniſter in Holy things (being deſcended from <hi>Ephraim</hi>) and therefore had no Right to ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord in the Tabernacle; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.1.</note> though his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeems not to have received any Command to bring him to the Tabernacle; though nothing ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears but her pious Gratitude; yet this was ſo well pleaſing to God, that he wore his Linnen Ephod, and miniſtred before the Lord. So bleſſed was the Child, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 26.</note> that he is ſaid to be <hi>in Favour both with God and Man.</hi> So much was he in God's favour, that while he was a Child, God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed with him from Heaven, that he revealed to him then his great ſecret Counſel of deſtroying the ſacred Family of <hi>Eli,</hi> and he made him his Prieſt, and great Prophet, and Judge of his People. There was no command for building the Schools of the Prophets; but there was a good and Religious deſign in it, and God ſo well accepted of it, that his holy Spirit overſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed them, and they received the Gift of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy frequently, and ſeldom was there a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet but out of theſe Colleges. Religious Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is a Conſecration of Children, a returning them to the hand that gave them: Which pious intention being ſo acceptable to <hi>the Father of Lights, the Giver of every good and perfect Gift,</hi> puts them into the likelieſt way of that Heavenly Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47338:6"/>which gives the increaſe to the plantings and waterings of Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Second Part.</head>
               <p>This laſt Conſideration is therefore of more moment, becauſe if we paſs to the <hi>Second</hi> ſort of advantages of good Education, <hi>viz.</hi> the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our natural Faculties, and adorning them with Sciences and Arts: This Heavenly influence goes thither too, and meets our Induſtry; it over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhadows all Learned Education, it facilitates and accompliſhes that. Wherefore as we enter into this ſecond Head, let us not leave behind us the laſt Conſideration.</p>
               <p>It has not pleaſed the Wiſdom of the Creator to give us the power of adding much to the Body, there is little for Diſcipline to do there; and that is only in ſuch motions as the Mind has the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of. We cannot alter the pulſe of the Heart, we cannot change our Complexion, nor give our Bodies another Conſtitution: We <hi>cannot add a Cubit to our ſtature, nor make one Hair white or black.</hi> But though his Wiſdom has not made us improvable in that part in which we reſemble Beaſts; yet his good Providence has made us exceedingly capable of improvement there where we are like himſelf. We may add Cubits, great additions of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to the Mind; its conſtitution and temper is capable of great amendments; of rough it may be made ſmooth and pliable; its vehement Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47338:7"/>moderated, its wanderings regulated, and brought into good order. The very firſt appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that the Soul makes, is in a capacity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving increaſe; which excellent things (the excellency and honour of Man) are the Fruits of a prudent and manly Education, which I intend to repreſent more particularly.</p>
               <p>But, as I ſaid, we muſt not forget that influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which Religious nurture, and the Divine bleſſing, has even upon the improvements of the natural Powers in the ways of Learning, and all uſeful and commendable knowledge in the World. God himſelf pleading with <hi>Job,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Job</hi> 38.36</note> puts this queſtion, <hi>Who hath put Wiſdom in the inward parts? Or who hath given Underſtanding to the Heart? Solomon,</hi> who ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts to educate Children, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 2.6.</note> anſwers thus, <hi>The Lord giveth Wiſdom.</hi> There is a Spirit in Man, ſays <hi>Elihu,</hi> and the inſpiration of the Almighty giveth Underſtanding. God gave to the four Children which the King of <hi>Babylon</hi> brought up, <hi>Knowledge,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and skill in all Learning and Underſtanding. Solomon</hi> after his improvements under the care of his Father, (a wiſe and religious Ruler) received a mighty addition of Wiſdom, of skill in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and natural knowledge by his Prayer, who ſtill recommends Education. The skill of the Husbandman and the Artificer, the Art of Trafficking, and the power of gathering Riches, the conduct of Warriours is from the ſame Bleſſing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47338:7"/>on the Labours of Men. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Doth the Plowman Plow all day to Sow? Doth he open and break the Clods of his Ground?</hi> Says the Almighty in <hi>Iſaiah.</hi> Who taught him the way? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 26.</note> 
                  <hi>His God doth inſtruct him to diſcretion, and doth teach him.</hi> God likewiſe changes his People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> leſt when they enter into the good Land, and diſpoſſeſs their Enemies, and grow Rich, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dcut.</hi> 8.17, 18.</note> they ſhould ſay in their Hearts, <hi>My Power, and the might of my Hand, hath gotten me this Wealth: But thou ſhalt remember the Lord thy God, for it is he that giveth thee Power to get Wealth.</hi> The wiſdom of the Captains, the valour of the Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, the victory in the day of Battel, the power of getting Riches when they were ſetled, came all from the ſame bountiful hand. There is an imperceptible Spring that guides our motions, and ſecretly gives ſpeed and happineſs even to our thoughts. And though the Operation be ſmooth and ſilent, yet it is not therefore the leſs power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; for the mightieſt Operations are moſt unob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable. Our bleſſed Saviour ſpeaking of the Spirit of Regeneration, compares it to a breath of Wind, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>John</hi> 3.8</note> of which one <hi>cannot tell whence it cometh and whither it goeth:</hi> One cannot ſay, lo! here it comes, or lo! there it goes: We cannot ſec at what paſſage the good thought entred, nor ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how the good Spirit infuſes a pious deſire; <hi>ſo is every one that is born of the Spirit.</hi> The Power by which the Goſpel conquered Nations, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47338:8"/>ſubdued mighty Kings, was not a boiſterous force, but a calm might: <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven cometh not by Obſervation.</hi> The great ruling Powers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in nature are as undiſcernable in their way, as irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtible. We ſee the Sun-ſhine, and we feel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his warmth; but we diſcern not how he enters into the Bowels of the Earth; how his little Atoms ſteal into the ſecret pores of Plants; how he impregnates Nature with new life. He ſeems to our Eye to ſtand ſtill, when he <hi>cometh forth like a Bridegroom out of his Chamber, and rejoyceth as a ſtrong Man to run his Race,</hi> and works wondrous things as he goes. We feel not how our own Spirits move, how they ſtart and fly as quick as we think, from one end of our Nerves to the other: If we ſay go, they are gone, and our Limbs are moved; but how, we know not: We do not feel them run, we cannot find their Channels and Poſts, we cannot diſcern the meaning of our Commands over them, how they reach them, and are applied to them: Neither are the Springs of our own thoughts apparent to Obſervation. So undiſcernable, and ſo puiſſant is the bleſſing of God on the ſtudies and labours of Men. How elſe came it into the Plowman's mind to venture the firſt Experiment of flinging his Corn away into the Dirt? What skill in the Laws of Nature, what Rules in Logic would aſſure him, that he ſhould ſee a rewarding Reſurrection
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47338:8"/>of it again, any more than if he ſowed a Pearl, or a Diamond? He did not learn it from the ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the ſcattered Seeds of the firſt voluntary Crop of the Earth; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 129.6, 7.</note> for theſe are but <hi>as the Grass, upon the Houſe tops, which withereth before it groweth up, wherewith the Mower filleth not his hand, nor he that bindeth ſheaves his boſom.</hi> It was his God that did firſt inſtruct him to Diſcretion, and did teach him. From whence elſe came the Invention of the many unaccountable Medicines in Phyſic? The many Arts which Men ſeem rather to have ſtumbled on by chance, than found by ſtrength of Reaſon and Method? Such as the Notes in Muſic, Printing, Proſpective Glaſſes, and the like? Whence comes it to paſs that one Age is Learned, and another Dark? Or how came this days public thought into your minds, paſſed by, by ſo many of our Predeceſſors? There is an unſeen Hand that guides all our thoughts and reaſonings, which gives you your powers to manage your Studies, Trades, and Buſineſs; which over-rules the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of all, and orders them to your private, and the public ends, as God pleaſes.</p>
               <p>While this unſeen Spring moves in our ſetting out, and all the courſe of our Life, the effects of careful Inſtitution of Children are very great and uſeful, and will appear in ſome meaſure in theſe following inſtances.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:47338:9"/>
               <p n="1">1. For firſt, Diſcipline teaches them to learn to live by Government, to gain ſome ſway over their own deſires; it keeps them within compaſs, and in order, which puts a manlineſs into the Mind, and a good compoſure in their Thoughts. The very diſuſing them from the fond Careſſes of home, from the tenderneſs of the Parent, and the compliance of the Houſe, which makes them peeviſh and untoward in their Humour, unſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in their Deſires, croſs and unruly, and lays the Foundation of a miſerable life; the very diſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, I ſay, from theſe expectations, teaches them to content themſelves with leſs, and inures them by little and little to ſelf-denial, one of the happieſt portions in this life. The fear of a watchful Eye over them, takes away that negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent looſneſs of Spirit which is apt to ſway in that Age, and begets Care and Obſervation. They are apt alſo through fear to grow quick in obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the meaſures of Juſtice and Equity; becauſe they quickly feel the ſmart of the contrary in their Governor, and are ready enough to complain of it; and becauſe alſo their own Injuries are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently called to an account.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Good Education lays the Principles of ſound Knowledge, which though ſmall at firſt, at laſt becomes great and uſeful. The Maſters leading their Obſervation, as they read of great examples, and wiſe ſayings; their illuſtrating and helping
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47338:9"/>them to gather into their Store-houſes profitable Propoſitions, inſtilling alſo frequently their own good Counſels, furniſhes them with a greater Treaſure than themſelves are aware of; for though the Seeds be little, and ſcarce reſemble the after-Fruit, yet they increaſe and branch forth, as their Reaſon grows, and what ſeems to lie buried at firſt, and unobſerved even by themſelves, ſprouts forth of it ſelf afterwards. And opportunity awakens the Memory, and ſhews the uſefulneſs of the Note; as a Propoſition in <hi>Mathematics</hi> gives a clearer ſight of the fulneſs of an <hi>Axiom,</hi> which at firſt reading ſeemed to have little in't. And this is the more advantagious, by reaſon of a certain ſtrange, but natural readineſs in Men, to remember the firſt impreſſions of their Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; in ſo much that the things which we heard or ſaw when we were Children, return more quickly to our thoughts oftentimes, than what we met with but a few days ſince.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That which fructifies all the Knowledge they have got, and is of more profit than the bare ſtock gained at School, is the enlarging and ſtrengthening the faculties of the Soul, the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powering her to increaſe her Treaſure farther. As in learning to Write, we value not the Copies we have written out, we ſcarce ever caſt an Eye upon them afterwards. That which we aim'd at was the dextrous uſe of the Hand, by which we
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47338:10"/>are able eaſily to do much more; ſo 'tis likewiſe the growth of the faculties that is the chief im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Education, by which the Mind is able to enrich her ſelf, though her former ſtock ſhould be loſt.</p>
               <p>The ſetling the Mind conſtantly upon Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, teaches a Man afterward to fix upon buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The not ſuffering his Childhood to taſt of idleneſs, but keeping him conſtantly going on, at laſt makes Labour as delightful as Play; partly by the power of cuſtom, partly by the pleaſure of gaining little victories over things that were difficult, by Commendations, by Emulations, and Triumphs over others, and a taſt of ſome ſweetneſs in Knowledge.</p>
               <p>Again, the frequent change of their Work, does both make the Labour eaſie (one being a recreation to the other) and that change alſo makes a Man afterward more ready to turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf quickly to the ſuddain importunities, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious changes of Affairs.</p>
               <p>The care that is uſed in examining the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Authors, and every little thing in a Word, 'till the meaning be hit exactly; teaches them to do the ſame afterward, to dive more readily into the minutes of buſineſs, and to let nothing paſs.</p>
               <p>The very agitation of the Mind makes its facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties luſty and healthy. The exerciſe of the fancy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47338:10"/>teaches it to open its Wings and flutter, and then to venture from ſhorter to more large and bold flights, 'till at laſt it ſoares freely and loftily, and looks upon things, the Proſpect opening it ſelf endleſly to the imagination as ſhe paſſes on, and giving the Mind an opportunity of viewing the varieties of the World, and of comparing things, and ſurveying their ſimilitudes and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, 'till at length by little degrees we learn in the operations of the fancy, to judge.</p>
               <p>The uſing Children to gather Obſervations, is one of the firſt occaſions of kindling a love of Learning. For thereby they ſee they have done ſomething, and rejoyce in their ſtrength, they compute their Gains, and look upon their Wealth, and learn to hoard up, and grow into a generous covetouſneſs after more; and when that deſign once grows into them, Induſtry and Vigilance carry on the Work apace. Eſpecially when the manly reaſonable Invention begins to open like the breaking forth of the Morning: When the Soul examins her ſtores, and finds ſome Reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings glittering like Jewels upon the entrance of light into a dark Room, and ſhe rejoyces to find a Treaſure within her ſelf, which ſhe never dream'd of.</p>
               <p>Finally, the frequent correction of the Errors of Invention, teaches both to obſerve the inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies of the fancy in her flights, and alſo to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47338:11"/>examin her own ſteps exactly, to go back and conſider all over again, to obſerve what occaſioned her miſtakes, and how to prevent them for the future. This uſe teaches us afterwards to correct our own reaſonings, and put our thoughts in order, and to try in what method we may more eaſily expedite our doubts, and find out truth, when we enter into deeper ſearches; a thing of wonderful uſe in all our following progreſs in Knowledge. And on theſe two laſt Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions vaſt things depend.</p>
               <p>It is not improbable, that that mighty diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence which we ſee between the famous Men of the World, and others, proceeds not ſo much from the natural Parts which they brought into the World, as firſt from a felicity in well placing a few early thoughts upon ſome noble deſign, which inflamed their Spirits, reigned in all their thoughts, and infuſed an earneſt care of perſuing their belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved end: And then, ſecondly, from an exact Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their own-ſteps, which ſetled them in good methods of conſidering and reaſoning. The famous <hi>Henry Stevens</hi> ſays of himſelf, That while he was a Boy, he fell in love with the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue, ſo fond and amorous he was, (ſo he expreſſes himſelf) that he courted it day and night with all the importunity, care, and addreſs that he could poſſibly. And how much he gained upon that difficult uncertain Dame, his <hi>Theſaurus
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47338:11"/>Graecae linguae,</hi> and other Labours witneſs to the World. <hi>Tully</hi> ſeems to have lighted, when young, upon ſome ſuch glorious thought as this, that <hi>Rome</hi> might as well out-do <hi>Athens</hi> in Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as her and the reſt of the World in other great things; for he is very often touching upon the ſtring, and his deſign of the glory of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence was reigning in him very early; for his Book of <hi>Rhetorical Invention</hi> was written when he was little above Twenty years old. <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> (whom <hi>Tully</hi> particularly emulated) was, before him, ſmitten with the like thought, by hearing an excellent Oration, to which his Maſter carried him when he was a Boy, and one it ſeems of no excellent Parts, but mightily ſet upon a deſign in a lucky hour. And this became to him quickneſs, invention, and eloquence. Of late days the great <hi>De Cartes</hi> was bleſt in his youth with an unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiable deſire after Philoſophy, and in all things clear evidence of truth. In order thereto, one of his fruitful thoughts was the keeping his reaſon true to her Work; the care of proceeding metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically and ſteadily in all his Meditations. And his conſtancy in this one care produced excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Fruits in him, before he wrote himſelf Man. As if, when it pleaſes Almighty God to produce ſome glorious Lights in the World, he need only to put a good quality of motion into great Orbs of dark and ſluggiſh Matter, fixing ſome Laws to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47338:12"/>be obſerved in all their motions: And immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately the <hi>Vortices</hi> go on with the Work them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if they were inſpired, and taken with the deſign: They ſort themſelves and gather toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their lucid parts in heaps at their Centers, and forthwith there appear glorious Lights, and all is tranſparent from the bottoms to the vaſt Superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. As if one great Man differed from another great Man in Glory, according as one choſe a greater, the other a leſſer Sphere to move in, together with the different celerities and <hi>conatus</hi> that were put into them. As ſuppoſe, one youth lighting upon a pleaſant conceit, and meeting applauſe and ſmiles, pleaſes himſelf, and being taken with it, plays with the ambition of the like wit, and ſpins in that narrow Circle all his days, and never goes beyond it. Another deſigns a more noble ſtudy, but ſtill is ſtreightned by ſelfiſhneſs, and vain-glory. Another aims at the beſt part of knowledge, and deſigns it the glory of his God, and the good of Men, and moves in a large Sphere, and ſhines with a greater luſter, and a more commending influence.</p>
               <p>And in this reſpect the places of public Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion have an advantage above the private, that they afford fairer opportunities of kindling and cheriſhing theſe great deſigns. I need not trouble you with the envious compariſon; for, allowing that private places are in ſome reſpects ſafer,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47338:12"/>
                  <hi>viz.</hi> by reaſon of a narrower inſpection than the larger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet it muſt be allowed, that private Schools uſually fare beſt, under the care of ſuch who have brought with them the experience of their public nurture, and moreover public and Royal Encouragements draw to thoſe places Men of greater skill. But, letting that alone, this is that which I aim at, That the ſparks that would go out of themſelves for want of Fewel, or be ſuffocated in too narrow a compaſs, have larger play here, and more encouragement to feed their Flame. Here we have opportunities of compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our own endeavours with others, of poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing our ſelves by them that do better, of raiſing our hopes by ſeeing others whom we ſeem to gain upon. The emulations here are more frequent among our equals, and the ſucceſs of Battels being uncertain, ſometimes we are fluſht with a Victory, and anon aſhamed a little by the croſs chance of War. So Induſtry is kept up between Glory and Shame. And theſe ingenuous ſtrifes turn the Toil into Play:
<q>— Studio fallente laborem.</q>
In public places alſo the Contentions are more warm, for here the Victories on the one hand are more open and conſpicuous, and ſo more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable; and on the other hand the ſhame more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47338:13"/>dreadful. For, to theſe youthful combatants, 'tis as if either the Senate were decreeing them a Triumph, and the neighbouring States were to ſend them in their <hi>aurum coronarium;</hi> or elſe they were to be led in ſcorn behind their inſulting Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Chariot.</p>
               <p>There are two ſpecial advantages of this kind, almoſt proper to the place of our Education, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned queſtionleſs by the Religious Wiſdom of our Royal Founder for our good; whoſe deſign ſeems a little to reſemble the policy of that great Shepherd <hi>Jacob,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.37, 38, &amp;c.</note> by which he gain'd the ſtronger Lambs. For firſt we were placed in a retirement from the World, and yet in the midſt of an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Society, adorned with Learned Men, and grave Divines, who (beſides their good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels they may inſtil, their overſight of the youth, the reverence they infuſe into them, the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements they can give to the pregnant and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and checks to the lazy and extravagant) afford alſo by their preſence and example, a lively influence to them that are to be brought up there; who beholding every day ſomthing of goodneſs to be imitated, of excellency to be admired, are apt to deſire and endeavour to be like them. They ſee that in its perfection which they are labouring after, which is a ready way to put that Spring into their young heads which I have been ſpeaking of,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47338:13"/>that ſets them on work. There alſo they have before them an excellent pattern of Unity. Secondly, the Royal Founder deſigning his School partly for <hi>Collegiats,</hi> and partly for others indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently, the former (whoſe hopes neceſſitate them to a greater Induſtry than ordinary) are helps to the latter, for their induſtry ſpurs on the reſt. And in a large number of Perſons of different parts, 'tis much if there be not one Egregious, who will put Life and Spirit into the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. Which is the more likely to take effect for this reaſon, becauſe 'tis natural for all of them, from one end to the other, to obſerve who is the leading lad; he is their Maſter of boaſting, they rejoyce in him, they ſpeak of him with bragging wherever they go.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Third Part.</head>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of the advantages of Education in Religion, and other Knowledge, all which in the <hi>Third</hi> place turn to a greater account, the more <hi>early</hi> Children are imbued therein, whether we conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, The gaining of Time, which ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly paſſes, and ſo irreſiſtibly, that all the Powers in nature can neither command, nor oblige a moment of it to ſtand ſtill for us, and when it is paſt, is impoſſible to be purchaſed again; the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47338:14"/>loſs of which is lamented moſt heartily by the wiſeſt of Men. And no wonder, ſince the whole Portion that is allotted to any of us, is ſo ſhort for the buſineſs we have to do in't, that there is little to ſpare for the quickeſt Man. Now the ſooner we begin, the greater improvements may be timely made; and when we are fitted early for the buſineſs of life, the longer time we have of making good uſe thereof. Inſtruction comes too late when we are going out of the World, or when we ſhould be uſing of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As for Religious Education, 'tis neceſſary to begin that early, becauſe of the evil Inclinations which proceed from the corruption of our Nature; for let us begin as ſoon as we can, Nature is before-hand with us: Wherefore we have no reaſon to give her more advantage againſt us by delay. The Weeds need not be ſown, you need not Plow, nor manure the Ground for them: 'Tis but letting them alone, and they riſe and ſpread apace, as if they had an original Right to the Ground, and the very dirtineſs of the Earth were their Seed: So that wickedneſs comes up ſo faſt, and ſo ſoon grows into rank Habits; that as 'tis impoſſible totally to prevent its being, ſo 'tis very difficult to prevent its quick growth, ſoon enough to overcome it. Religion
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47338:14"/>wants a cultivated Ground, and an extraordinary Seed; and much of that (when 'tis ſown) is apt to be ſcattered by the way, or devoured by the Fowls of the Air, or choaked by Thorns, or withered by Heat. 'Tis a tender Seed, ſubject to ſundry injuries, none of which Sin is liable to. There needs no care to be wicked, nor ſerious thought, nor wiſe conſideration; the abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all thought of what one does, gives it increaſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Early nurture of Children in Religion is neceſſary, becauſe of the evil Examples, and treacherous Inſtruction, which they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe apt to be miſled by, after which all better Inſtitution becomes feeble and uſeleſs, for what good is to be done with a Lad, after a corrupt Nature has been made worſe by Art? After he has fallen into the Education of a Slave, or the management of the impious Hangby's of the Family, who inſtruct their young Maſter in Pride, and ſwell his Heart with the expectation of an Eſtate, 'till they have made him impregnable againſt the fear of God, and all prudent Advice, leſt he ſhould grow wiſe, and good enough to diſcard them? But if you begin betimes to plant pious Principles into the Child; before he be miſimproved; Religious thoughts may be infuſed
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47338:15"/>into him, and through the bleſſing of God, become powerful enough to rectifie the byas of natural inclination in a great meaſure, for we have ſome helps on Nature's ſide too; the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a God is Natural, and a part of us, and ſo is the ſenſe of Good and Evil, and the preſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gings of Immortality.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Timely Education is of like benefit in the gaining human Knowledge, becauſe of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility, and yielding Humility that is at firſt in Children; and becauſe 'tis eaſier to guide the Reaſon before it has uſed it ſelf to wandring. Moreover, the Mind is capable of a directer view of Truth, before it is filled with prejudices, and perverſe notions of things. Cogitation is natural to the Soul, and ſolid Knowledge is that which delights her. She is made to deſire Truth, and Truth is made to ſatisfie her; but for want of care and order ſhe becomes often alienated from her own Nature, and delights in Traſh rather than her proper Food, by reaſon of a delight we take in variety. For 'tis equally hard to us not to think at all, and to think on ſteadily upon one thing; and the Mind had rather play hard (like a Child) than work eaſily. For becauſe Truth does not lye open to the firſt eaſie Thought, but dwells in a difficult and obſcure receſs; the Mind
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47338:15"/>is amazed at the difficulty, and is afraid to go in and purſue her, but runs away ſcared with the darkneſs, and delights with the firſt appearances, and ſo paſſes away from one thing to another, 'till ſhe be filled with miſtakes, and uſed to wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring; and then 'tis hard to bring her to conſider orderly. To prevent this, there muſt be timely care taken to make the firſt ſteps eaſie and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to uſe the Mind to care and conſtancy.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The early Education of Children (as their years and capacity require) prevents thoſe omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous diſcouragements which they meet with, who enter later than ordinary; for he that comes late is prejudiced the firſt moment, becauſe he muſt be placed below thoſe of his own Age, which makes him look'd upon as the dull Child. And that is apt to damp him in his own conceit, and make him think that he is ſo; 'till by deſponding he become what he feared others thought, and what himſelf imagined. Whereas, on the other hand, he that has gained a ſtep before his Equals in years, is impregnated with hopes, and a deſire of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his Poſt that he has gained; and finding auſpicious Eyes upon him, and a love to aſſiſt the pregnant, he receives, and gives himſelf encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to go on and ſucceed.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:47338:16"/>
               <p n="6">6. To this we may add <hi>Solomon</hi>'s weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Train him up early while he is a <hi>Child</hi> in a good way, and then he will not forſake it <hi>when he is old.</hi> The ſooner you give him Inſtruction, the more likely it is to laſt 'till Age. Whereas one would think that the later any thing was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the mind, the more likely the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory ſhould be to retain it 'till we grow old, and what was learnt very early, ſhould wear away by degrees in ſuch a length of time, and diſappear quite before old Age; (ſo many Actions intervening, ſo many anxious Thoughts and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns in Manhood entring into the Mind, likely to diſpoſſeſs the former, and ſo many things being more freſhly pictured in the memory, ſo great length of time remaining to make the firſt lively Colours look faint, if not decay quite.) 'Tis here all quite contrary. The ſooner you begin, the more certainly all things retain their livelineſs, though there be the longer time for them to be defaced. Neither is this without reaſon. For the ſooner the apprehenſions of Goodneſs, and worthy Knowledge are impreſſed upon the Soul, the fairer and lovelier are the <hi>Idea's.</hi> The Table is the clearer for you to draw upon, the Mind has no miſapprehenſions and prejudicate Notions, which ſully the Soul: There are no vicious Habits,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47338:16"/>nor perverſe Reaſons to keep out Goodneſs and Truth. The Mind at firſt is more tender and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and therefore receives the impreſſion the deeper into it. Wherefore the earlier the impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are made, they are more delightful, and are retained with greater pleaſure, and that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure increaſes every day, as experience ſhews the ſweetneſs and uſefulneſs of Religious and Wiſe Counſels, which makes them grow into the Mind: Add to this, that faſt retention in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, of things done in our minority, which was mentioned before. It is as true alſo on the other hand, that if you <hi>train up a Child in the way that he ſhould</hi> not <hi>go, when he is old he will not depart from</hi> that neither. This is apparent, as well in the faults of the Will, as in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of the Underſtanding. 'Tis almoſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to deal with an overgrown Sinner, that from his Childhood has given himſelf over to wickedneſs. There is alſo a fixing of Errors in old Men, (who have not been uſed to the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity of examining their Opinions, and doubting of their Abilities) you may as well draw Blood from ſome, as convince them of an error or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that was in repute in their youth; for they grow <hi>Axioms</hi> in them; by them they judge of all arguing, and therefore there is no way for a new Argument to take place.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:47338:17"/>
               <p>Laſtly, The earlier we are improved, the greater Power, the longer Seaſon, and ſo the more opportunities we gain of bringing Glory to the great God, and doing good to Men, which two things are the grand Ends of the beſt inſtitution, and the moſt glorious happineſs of this life; they are the true Reaſons for which one would deſire to be well Educated. A Man had even as good have been born a Fool, or dropt into ſome dark corner of the World, and never ſee what Breeding or Learning means; as be furniſhed with great Abilities and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, only to do miſchief, to manage Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to head Seditions and Schiſms, and to be witty againſt God and Virtue, and the common ſenſe of Mankind.</p>
               <p>I have named as many of the Benefits of training up Children in the way they ſhould go, as I could think of; becauſe the Conſideration of them leads to a juſt value, and ſo to a grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful acknowledgment of them to the great Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the World; for who ever was thankful for what he never eſteemed, or eſteemed what he never thought of? I thought it not amiſs to take notice of ſome things which ſeem ſmall, both becauſe their Effects are great, and becauſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47338:17"/>alſo they lead us to a higher value of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For how much Gratitude do you owe to God, who after he had endowed you with na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Abilities, took care to plant you in a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Soil, where they might increaſe, and you might excel other Men in that which is the Glory of Man? Who took care to place you where your Minds might be imbued with a ſenſe of true Religion and Virtue, and improved with ſuch Knowledge, as might make you ſhine, and adorn the Church and State? What ſhould we render to God, who inſpires the Hearts of Kings with ſuch charitable Thoughts towards us? What ſhould we return to the living God, who took care to lay in our Minds the Seeds of a bleſſed Immortality? Not only an Immortality in Fame and Glory among Men, which gives but little refreſhment to the aſhes of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious; but an Immortality in real Glory and Happineſs. This was a Care which we were incapable of beſtowing upon our ſelves, then when we moſt needed it; and if we had ſtayed 'till we became Men, it would have been too late, for by that time our Reaſon had been ſnarled, and all our Powers had become untune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:47338:18"/>
               <p>I cannot better repreſent to you this great goodneſs of God, than in the words of the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 38.24, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>The Wiſdom of a Wiſe Man cometh by opportunity of leiſure, and he that hath little buſiness ſhall become Wiſe. How can he get Wiſdom that holdeth the Plow, that glorieth in the Goad, that driveth Oxen, and is occupied in their Labours, and whoſe talk is of Bullocks? He giveth his mind to make Furrows, and is diligent to give the Kine Fodder.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 28.</note> The <hi>Smith</hi> alſo ſitting <hi>by the Anvil, and conſidering the Iron-work, the Vapour of the Fire waſteth his Fleſh, and he ſigheth with the heat of the Furnace: The noiſe of the Hammer and the Anvil is ever in his Ears.</hi> And ſo he deſcribes the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 32.</note> the <hi>Graver,</hi> the <hi>Potter: Men without whom a City cannot be inhabited.</hi> But they are confined to an Imployment too narrow for Knowledge, and converſe of Wiſe Men. They are not likely to be called forth to a larger Sphere of public Service. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 33.</note> 
                  <hi>They ſhall not be ſought for in public Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, nor ſit in the Congregation, they ſhall not ſit in the Judges Seat.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 39.1. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>But he that giveth his mind to the Law of the moſt High, and is occupied in the Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, will ſeek out the Wiſdom of the ancient, he will keep the ſayings of renowned Men; he ſhall ſerve among great Men, and appear before Princes, he will travel through ſtrange Countrey's, for he hath
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47338:18"/>tried the Good and Evil among Men.</hi> And ſo he goes on elegantly. I will not trouble you with all of it, only conclude with his Exhortation ſo ſuitable to this Aſſembly. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Hearken unto me ye Holy Children, and bud forth as the</hi> Roſe <hi>growing by the Brook of the Field. And give ye a ſweet ſavour as Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and flouriſh as a</hi> Lilly; <hi>ſend forth a ſweet ſmell, and ſing a Song of Praiſe; Bless the Lord in all his Works.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
